export const CHEMISTRYB2018 = [

{
section:  "Section A",
id: "question1ai",
question:  "1ai. Define the term fermentation",
definition:  "Define the term fermentation Answer: Fermentation is the conversion of glucose or sugar to ethanol {alcohol} and release of carbon(iv) oxide as a by-product. It can also be defined as the decomposition or breakdown of glucose {starch or carbohydrate} to ethanol {alcohol} and release of carbon (iv) oxide.",
},

{
id: "question1aii",
question:  "1aii. Name the catalyst that can be used for this process",
definition:  "Name the catalyst that can be used for this process Answer: Yeast/Zymase",
},

{
id: "question1b",
question:  "1b. Name two factors which determine the choice of an indicator for an acid-base titration",
definition:  "Name two factors which determine the choice of an indicator for an acid-base titration Answer: \n  The colour of the indicator must be sharp \n  Strength of the acid and the base involved in the filtration",
},

{
id: "question1c",
question:  "1c. Consider the following reaction equation: nFe  +  H2SO4  →   FeSO4  +  H2",
definition:  "Consider the following reaction equation: Fe  +  H2SO4  →   FeSO4  +  H2 Calculate the mass of unreacted iron when 5.0g of iron reacts with 10cm3 of 1.0mol/dm3 H2SO4 [Fe = 56.0] Solution 1 mole of H2SO4 = 1 mole of Fe \n1000cm3 → 56g \n10cm3   → x g \n= 561000×10561000×10 \n= 0.56g \nMass of unreacted Fe = 5 – 0.56g \n= 4.44g",
},

{
instruction:  "Calculate the mass of unreacted iron when 5.0g of iron reacts with 10cm3 of 1.0mol/dm3 H2SO4 [Fe = 56.0]",
instruction:  "1d. Name one:",
id: "question1di",
question:  "1di. Heavy chemical used in electrolytic cells",
definition:  "Heavy chemical used in electrolytic cells Answer: Tetraoxosulphate (vi) acid",
},

{
id: "question1dii",
question:  "1dii. Fine chemical used in textile industries",
definition:  "Fine chemical used in textile industries Answer: Dies",
},

{
id: "question1e",
question:  "1e. Explain briefly how a catalyst increases the rate of a chemical reaction.",
definition:  "Explain briefly how a catalyst increases the rate of a chemical reaction. Answer: A catalyst provides an alternative pathway for the reaction to occur by lowering the activation energy.",
},

{
id: "question1fi",
question:  "1fi. Write the chemical formula for the product formed when ethanoic acid reacts with ammonia",
definition:  "Write the chemical formula for the product formed when ethanoic acid reacts with ammonia Answer: CH3COONH4",
},

{
id: "question1fii",
question:  "1fii. Give the name of the product formed in 1f.1i.",
definition:  "Give the name of the product formed in (f)(i) Answer:  Ammonium ethanoate",
},

{
id: "question1g",
question:  "1g. List three properties of aluminum that makes it suitable for the manufacture of drinks cans",
definition:  "List three properties of aluminum that makes it suitable for the manufacture of drinks cans Answer:  \n It is malleable \n  Does not corrode \n  Has low density \n  Does not react with the drink",
},

{
id: "question1h",
question:  "1h. State two industrial uses of alkyl alkanoates",
definition:  "State two industrial uses of alkyl alkanoates Answer:  \n  Production of soaps \n  Flavouring agents \n  Solvents \n  Making of perfumes",
},

{
id: "question1i",
question:  "1i. Name two steps involved in the crystallization of a salt from its solution",
definition:  "Name two steps involved in the crystallization of a salt from its solution Answer:  \n  Concentration/heating of the solution \n  Cooling of the solution \n  Filtration",
},

{
id: "question1j",
question:  "1j. List two effects of global warming",
definition:  "List two effects of global warming Answer:  \n  Flooding \n  Severe drought \n  Climate change",
},

{
id: "question2ai",
question:  "2ai. State the collision theory of reaction rates.",
definition:  "State the collision theory of reaction rates. Answer: Collision theory states that atoms, molecules, ions, particles, or reactants involved in a chemical reaction must collide before the reaction can take place.",
},

{
id: "question2aii",
question:  "2aii. Using the collision theory, explain briefly how temperature can affect the rate of a chemical reaction.",
definition:  "Using the collision theory, explain briefly how temperature can affect the rate of a chemical reaction. Answer: When the temperature is increased or decreased, the reacting molecules gain or lose kinetic energy and move faster or slower.",
},

{
id: "question2bi",
question:  "2bi. Sketch a graphical representation of Charles’ law.",
definition:  "",
},

{
id: "question2bii",
question:  "2bii. Calculate the volume of oxygen that would be required for the complete combustion of 2.5 moles of ethanol at s.t.p. [molar volume at s.t.p = 22.4 dm3]",
definition:  "Calculate the volume of oxygen that would be required for the complete combustion of 2.5 moles of ethanol at s.t.p. [molar volume at s.t.p = 22.4 dm3]  \nGiven: moles of ethanol = 2.5 ; molar volume at s.t.p = 22.4dm3 Find: volume of oxygen? C2H5OH(aq)  +  3O2(g) 3H2O(l)  + 2CO2(g) \nFrom the equation, 1 mole of ethanol requires 3 x 22.4dm3 of oxygen \n2.5 moles =  \n2.5×3×22.412.5×3×22.4\n1\n= 168.0dm3",
},

{
id: "question2ci",
question:  "2ci. Define esterification.",
definition:  "Define esterification. Answer: Esterification is the reaction between an alkanol and alkanol acid to produce an ester {alkanoate} and water in the presence of a mineral acid",
},

{
id: "question2cii",
question:  "2cii. Give two uses of alkanoates.",
definition:  "Give two uses of alkanoates. \n  Used as solvents {e.g. for paints, adhesives, nails} \n  Used in perfumes/cosmetic \n  Used in production of soaps \n  Used in artificial flavouring",
},

{
id: "question2ciii",
question:  "2ciii. Give the products of the alkaline hydrolysis of ethyl ethanoate.",
definition:  "Give the products of the alkaline hydrolysis of ethyl ethanoate.   Answer:  Ethanol and sodium athanoate or potassium ethanoate C2H5OH and CH3COONa or CH3COOK",
},

{
instruction:  "2d. A tin-coated plate and a galvanized plate were exposed for the same length of time.",
id: "question2di",
question:  "2di. Which of the two plates corrodes faster",
definition:  "Which of the two plates corrodes faster Answer: Tin-coated plate corrodes faster",
},

{
id: "question2dii",
question:  "2dii. Explain briefly your answer in 2(d)(i)",
definition:  "Explain briefly your answer in 2(d)(i) Answer:  Zinc is more reactive than tin i.e. higher in electrochemical series than tin. When the tin-coated plate is exposed, the plate goes into the solution {corrodes}. In Zinc-coated {galvanized} plate, it is the zinc that gets corroded, hence, protecting the plate better prevents the zinc-coated plate from corroding.",
},

{
id: "question3ai",
question:  "3ai. Draw the structure of the sixth member of the alkenes.",
definition:  "Draw the structure of the sixth member of the alkenes.",
},

{
id: "question3aii",
question:  "3aii. Calculate the relative molecular mass of the sixth member of the alkene.",
definition:  "Calculate the relative molecular mass of the sixth member of the alkene. Solution: C7H4 = (12 x 7)  +  (1 x 4) = 84 + 14 = 98",
},

{
id: "question3aii",
question:  "3aii. State one difference between cracking and reforming in the petroleum industry. [H = 1, C = 12]",
definition:  "Calculate the relative molecular mass of the sixth member of the alkene. Solution: C7H4 = (12 x 7)  +  (1 x 4) = 84 + 14 = 98",
},

{
id: "question3bi",
question:  "3bi. Define the term enthalpy of neutralization.",
definition:  "Define the term enthalpy of neutralization. Answer: Enthalpy of neutralization is the heat evolved when an acid reacts with a base to form one mole of water.",
},

{
id: "question3bii",
question:  "3bii. Describe briefly how the enthalpy of neutralization of the reaction of dilute hydrochloric acid and aqueous potassium hydroxide could be determined.",
definition:  "Describe briefly how the enthalpy of neutralization of the reaction of dilute hydrochloric acid and aqueous potassium hydroxide could be determined.   Answer: Equimolar solutions of hydrochloric acid and potassium hydroxide are prepared separately. A known volume of the acid is placed on a calorimeter and the temperature is recorded\nThe same volume of the potassium hydroxide solution at the same temperature is poured into the calorimeter and the mixture is stirred gently. The maximum temperature of the mixture is recorded\nHeat lost in the reaction = heat gain by the solution forme\nHeat of neutralization = mass of solution x specific heat capacity of water x change in temperature\nPrepare equimolar solution of HCI and NaOH separately. Measure an equal volume of acid and alkali into two separate beakers. Take the temperature of each of the solutions i.e. t1 and t\nFind the average of the two temperatures \nt1+\\nHeat lost in the reaction = t4 – t\n∆H neutralization = mass of solution x specific heat capacity of water x change in Temperature",
},

{
instruction:  "3c. An electrochemical cell is constructed with copper and silver electrodes.",
id: "question3ci",
question:  "3ci. State which of the electrodes will be the: \nI. anode\nII. cathode",
definition:  "State which of the electrodes will be the: I. anode Answer: Copper electrode (Anode) \nII. cathode Answer: Silver electrode (Cathode)",
},

{
id: "question3cii",
question:  "3cii. Give the reason for your answer in 3ci.",
definition:  "Give the reason for your answer in 3(c)(i). Answer: Silver has a more positive standard electrode potential than copper. Copper is more electropositive than silver; copper is higher in the electrochemical series.",
},

{
id: "question3ciii",
question:  "3ciii. State the type of reaction occurring at each electrode.",
definition:  "State the type of reaction occurring at each electrode. Answer: Anode – oxidation {occurs at the copper electrode} Cathode – reduction {occurs at the silver electrode}",
},

{
id: "question3civ",
question:  "3civ. Write a balanced equation for the overall cell reaction.",
definition:  "Write a balanced equation for the overall cell reaction.   Answer: Cu(s)  + 2A+(aq) → Cu2+(aq)  +  2Ag(s)",
},

{
id: "question3di",
question:  "3di. Name the compound formed when iron is exposed to moist air for a long time.",
definition:  "Name the compound formed when iron is exposed to moist air for a long time. Answer: Hydrated iron(iii) oxide",
},

{
id: "question3dii",
question:  "3dii. Write a balanced chemical equation for the reaction in 3di.",
definition:  "Write a balanced chemical equation for the reaction in 3(d)(i). Answer: 4Fe(s)  +  3O2(g)  +  2 x H2O(l) → 2Fe2O3 , x H2O. 4Fe(g) + 3O2(g)  +  2H2O → 2Fe2O3 . H2O",
},

{
id: "question3diii",
question:  "3diii. Name one ore of iron.",
definition:  "Name one ore of iron. Answer: \n  Haematite \n  Magnetite \n  Lamonite \n Iron Pyrites",
},

{
id: "question4ai",
question:  "4ai. Draw and label a diagram for the laboratory preparation of a dry sample of sulphur4IV.oxide.",
definition:  "Draw and label a diagram for the laboratory preparation of a dry sample of sulphur(IV)oxide.",
},

{
id: "question4aii",
question:  "4aii. Write a balanced chemical equation for the reaction in 4a.4i..",
definition:  "Write a balanced chemical equation for the reaction in (a)(i). Answer: Na2SO3(aq)  +  2HCl(aq) → 2NaCl(aq)  +  H2O(l)  +  SO2(g) \nOR K2SO3(aq)  +  2HCl(aq)  → 2KC(aq)  + H2O(l)  +  SO2(g)  \nOR Cu(s)  +  2H2SO4(aq) → CuSO4  +  2H2O(l)  + SO2(l)",
},

{
id: "question4aiii",
question:  "4aiii. State the precaution that must be taken in the preparation of the gas stated in 4a.4i..",
definition:  "State the precaution that must be taken in the preparation of the gas stated in (a)(i). Answer: It should be prepared in a fume chamber or cupboard",
},

{
id: "question4aiv",
question:  "4aiv. Give a reason why the precaution stated in 4a.4ii. must be taken.",
definition:  "Give a reason why the precaution stated in (a)(ii) must be taken. Answer: Because it is poisonous",
},

{
id: "question4bi",
question:  "4bi. State Dalton’s law of partial pressures.",
definition:  "State Dalton’s law of partial pressures. Answer: It states that for a mixture of gases which do not react, the total pressure is equal to the sum of the partial pressures of the individual gases.",
},

{
id: "question4bii",
question:  "4bii. The volume of a sample of methane collected over water at a temperature of 120C and a pressure of 700 \nmmHg was 30cm3. Calculate the volume of the dry gas at s.t.p. \n[Standard vapour pressure of water at 120C is 10mmHg]",
definition:  "Find: Volume of dry gas? \n𝑃1𝑉\n𝑇1\n= \n𝑃2𝑉\n𝑇2\nP1 = (700 – 10) mmHg = 690 mmHg \nT1 = 12 + 273 = 28k \nwhere T2 = 273 \nV2 = \n𝑃1𝑉1𝑇\n𝑃2𝑇1\n= \n690 𝑥 30 𝑥 273\n 𝑥 285\n= 26.10cm3",
},

{
id: "question4ci",
question:  "4ci. Write an equation for the reaction between chlorine and water.",
definition:  "Write an equation for the reaction between chlorine and water. Answer: Cl2  +  H2O   HCl  +  HClO",
},

{
id: "question4cii",
question:  "4cii. Why does litmus paper turn red when put in the resulting solution in 4c.4i.?",
definition:  "Why does litmus paper turn red when put in the resulting solution in (c)(i)?   Answer: H+ ions are released. HCl produced is acidic. HClO produced is acidic.",
},

{
id: "question4di",
question:  "4di. State the trend in the boiling points of chlorine, bromine and iodine.",
definition:  "State the trend in the boiling points of chlorine, bromine, and iodine. Answer: The boiling point of iodine is higher than that of bromine which itself is higher than that of chlorine in turn.  Boiling points increase from chlorine to iodine",
},

{
id: "question4dii",
question:  "4dii. Explain briefly why water has a higher boiling point than ammonia.",
definition:  "Explain briefly why water has a higher boiling point than ammonia. Answer: Water has a stronger hydrogen bond than ammonia because oxygen has two lone pairs of electrons but nitrogen has just one pair of electrons as an atom, oxygen is more electronegative than nitrogen",
},

{
instruction:  "5a. State two industrial uses of hydrogen.",
id: "question5ai",
question:  "5ai. Consider the equation below.",
definition:  "Answer:  \n  Used in the manufacture of plastics \n  Used for filling weather balloons \n  Manufacture of ammonia by the Haber process \n  Used in the manufacture of ammonia \n  Used as a reducing agent in the production of metals e.g. Cu and Pb, from their oxides \n  Hydrogen is used as rocket fuel/gaseous fuel \n  Hydrogen is used as a cooling gas in electric power generators.",
},

{
id: "question5aii",
question:  "5aii. State the type of hardness of water being removed as shown by the above equation.",
definition:  "Answer: Temporary hardness",
},

{
id: "question5aiii",
question:  "5aiii. Give two disadvantages of the hardness of water.",
definition:  "Answer: \n  Furring of kettles or pipes, causing blockage and consequently power wastes \n  Not suitable for drinking \n  Not suitable for use in tanning, textile, and paper production \n  Not suitable for laundry and many other domestic cleanings/wastes soap.",
},

{
id: "question5bi",
question:  "5bi. In the extraction of aluminum by electrolysis, graphite electrodes are used. State the disadvantages of using this type of electrode.",
definition:  "In the extraction of aluminum by electrolysis, graphite electrodes are used. State the disadvantages of using this type of electrode. Answer: At high temperatures, oxygen gas produced at the anode reacts with the graphite electrodes to form carbon (iv) oxide.",
},

{
id: "question5bii",
question:  "5bii. Calcium oxide reacts with water to form slaked line: \nI. Write a balanced equation for this reaction \nII. State one use of slaked line.",
definition:  "Calcium oxide reacts with water to form slaked line: \nI. Write a balanced equation for this reaction; Answer: CaO + H2O   →  Ca(OH)2 \nII. State one use of slaked line. Answer:  \n  Used to treat acidic soil \n  Used in the manufacture of glass \n  Used to make splasters, mortar, cement and to hold bricks \n▪  Used to purify water and in the removal of hardness from water.",
},

{
id: "question5ci",
question:  "5ci. What is meant by saponification?",
definition:  "What is meant by saponification? Answer: Saponification is the process in which fat or oil is boiled with alkali to produce soap {and propane -1, 2, 3 – triol}. It is the alkaline hydrolysis of fats and oils to produce soap.",
},

{
id: "question5cii",
question:  "5cii. List the raw materials needed for the manufacture of soap.",
definition:  "List the raw materials needed for the manufacture of soap. Fat and alkali are the two primary raw materials needed to manufacture soap. Depending on the intended application of the soap, sodium hydroxide or potassium hydroxide is generally used as an alkali.",
},

{
id: "question5ciii",
question:  "5ciii. Name the main by-product obtained from the manufacture of soap.",
definition:  "Name the main by-product obtained from the manufacture of soap. Answer: Propane -1, 2, 3 – triol",
},

{
instruction:  "5d. With the aid of chemical equations explain briefly how iron is extracted in the blast furnace using iron ore, coke and limestone as raw materials at the:",
id: "question5di",
question:  "5di. bottom of the furnace;",
definition:  "With the aid of chemical equations explain briefly how iron is extracted in the blast furnace using iron ore, coke, and limestone as raw materials at the: (i) bottom of the furnace Answer: The O2 in the hot air combines with the carbon {coke} to produce carbon (iv) oxide which reduces to carbon (ii) oxide \nC + O2 → CO2 \nCO2  + C  → 2CO",
},

{
id: "question5dii",
question:  "5dii. middle of the furnace",
definition:  "middle of the furnace Answer: The CaCO3 decomposes under great heat to form CO2 and CaO OR CaCO3 decomposes to remove the impurities {S1 O2} \nCaCO3 → CaO + CO2 \nCaO  + Si O2 → CaSiO3",
},

{
id: "question5diii",
question:  "5diii. top of the furnace.",
definition:  "top of the furnace. Answer: Iron (iii) oxide is reduced to metallic iron {Fe} Fe2O3  +  3CO →  2Fe  + 3CO2 OR Fe3SO4  +  4CO → 3Fe  +  4CO2",
},

{
}

]